<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Londons returne, after the decrease of the sicknes in a sermon (appointed for the Crosse) but preached in St. Pauls Church. Ianuary 8. 1637. By O.W. p.</title>
            <author>Whitbie, Oliver.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15068</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25371</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119857</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855063</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855063</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20533</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15068)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20533)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 945:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Londons returne, after the decrease of the sicknes in a sermon (appointed for the Crosse) but preached in St. Pauls Church. Ianuary 8. 1637. By O.W. p.</title>
                  <author>Whitbie, Oliver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by N. and I. Okes; and are to bee sold by Richard Whitaker, at the signe of the Kings Armes in Saint Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: O. Whitbie.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Plague --  England --  London --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20533:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20533:1"/>
            <p>LONDONS Returne, After the decreaſe of the SICKNES: In a Sermon (appointed for the <hi>Croſſe</hi>) but preached in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. PAULS CHVRCH. <hi>January</hi> 8. 1637.</p>
            <p>By <hi>O.W. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>And when he was come neere, he beheld the city, and wept over it, ſaying, &amp;c.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luk. 19.41.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>N. and I. Okes;</hi> and are to bee ſold by <hi>Richard Whitaker,</hi> at the ſigne of the Kings Armes in Saint <hi>Pauls Church-yard.</hi> 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20533:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20533:2"/>
            <head>To the truly noble, and my much honoured friend, <hi>John Puliney</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have read of gratitude, in Birds, and Beaſts; of a <hi>Lions</hi> thankefulneſſe to a <hi>Romane</hi> Captive; of a <hi>Storke</hi> which caſt a precious Stone into the boſome of a Maide, which had healed her of a wound: Which deeds of Nature doe ſpeake to me that Goſpel <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.37. <hi>Vade &amp; tu fac ſimiliter, Goe thou and doe likewiſe.</hi> Now if <hi>Solomon</hi> thought to ſhame the Sluggard into pains, by ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him to the buſie <hi>Ant;</hi> Ile thinke
<pb facs="tcp:20533:3"/>it, no diſparagement, to learne in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Schoole, gratitude of a Bird. Thoſe many favours of Love which your noble ſpirit hath heaped upon me, laid ſuch a ſtrickt ſiege to my thoughts, that I knew not how to reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue my ſelfe, but by this publike decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; wherein, whil'ſt I ſhew my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I proclaime my weakneſſe; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this cenſure (from the world) to bee a man guilty of gratitude: yet no matter, 'tis a leſſe crime to commit an errour, then to forget a friend: and if <hi>Naaman</hi> did not remember his maide, which told him of the Prophet, I dare ſay, his ingratitude was a fouler diſeaſe then his leproſie. The laſt Summer, when <hi>Divine Juſtice</hi> had ſcattered us over all the Land, your houſe was my
<pb facs="tcp:20533:3"/>noble <hi>Sanctuary;</hi> where I ſaw, as much Religion practiſed, as an <hi>Hypocrite</hi> can talke of; and ſuch reverent conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in your private Chappell, that obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience might there ſafely ſtand for a Lecture; and bending the knee (to the <hi>Jeſus</hi> of men) would not looſe a voyce, but get a bleſſing. And now, ſir, for my royall entertainement, I preſent you with a paper paiment, <hi>this poore Sermon,</hi> which wear's no coſtly dreſſe; preach'd in a time of ſadnes, when ſorrow is the beſt eloquence. To your hands I ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, and your religious Lady, who (to the glory of her Sex) ſees her ſelfe oftner in a Booke then in a Glaſſe, and is ſo enamour'd with ſaving knowledg, that ſhe reſembles the Bee, which lives in honey, or the Birds of the fortunate
<pb facs="tcp:20533:4"/>Ilands, which are nouriſhed with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes. Now the good will of him that dwelt in the <hi>Buſh,</hi> preſerve you both, and your virgin ſiſter (ſecond to none in <hi>Vertue</hi>) who now increaſeth the poore with <hi>Almes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mrs.</hi> Mary Puliney.</note> as ſhe will hereafter <hi>Heaven</hi> with a <hi>Saint:</hi> and the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> give you the bleſſing of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> the precious things of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and the precious things of the <hi>Earth;</hi> &amp; grant, that what you ſowe beneath, you may reape above; God Almighty lead you by the hands, from <hi>Grace</hi> to <hi>Glory;</hi> 'tis the prayer of him who is, and ever will bee</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your vertues bumble and devoted ſervant, <hi>O. WHITBIE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20533:4"/>
            <head>Londons Returne.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Text, <hi>Hoſea 6.</hi> verſ. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Come and let us returne to the Lord, for he hath torne and he will heale us; he hath broken, and he will bind us up.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Text, <hi>Hoſea 6.</hi> verſ. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>After two dayes he will revive us; the third day he will raiſe us up, and we ſhall live in his ſight.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eere are a ſort of good people met in my text, and I hope within mine eye too; and though we are not all of one blood, yet we are all of one buſineſſe; they and wee are now met, about <hi>a returne to the Lord.</hi> And the time fitly conſpires with our purpoſe, for the yeere is now returned; the Sun begins to returne, and lengthens the day; after him the Spring, and Fowles will follow: and moſt of you here are returned from your laſt yeeres exile, to your owne houſes, O ſtay not behind in the beſt and chiefe of all returnes, your returne to the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:20533:5"/>
            <p> Here is none in this, needes feare <hi>Solomons Va ſoli,</hi> woe to him that is alone; for if you will returne, you ſhall have a whole Nation to be are you company; the twelve Tribes are now ready to ſet forth: their way is our way, their caſe our caſe, even ſmiting and tearing, and their Phyſitian our Phyſitian: oh then let their voyce be ours, and every one of us ſay to our neighbour, as they here did, <hi>Venite &amp; revertamur ad Dominum, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words are a ſtory of the egreſſe, and regreſſe, of prodigal children, a cleare chriſtall glaſſe, wherein may bee ſeene the face, and perfect proportion of penitent mens converſion.</p>
            <p>Now as Travellers in a morning, will not ſtay at every man they meete, to enquire the way, but having tooke good direction in their Inne, paſſe on with ſpeede. No more will I now ſtand to diſpute with all expoſitors of theſe many wayes, which is the beſt, but leade you on like <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> by the way of the plaine, neither marching too furiouſly, like ſome <hi>Iehu's</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> who thinke to winne Heaven by their ſpurs, nor yet creeping a ſnailes pace with our laſie <hi>Solifidians,</hi> who would get to heaven too when they dye, and yet live with their armes a croſſe: but leade you fairely on, as <hi>Iacob</hi> did his wives children, and in your way deſire you to take notice of theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>Iſraels</hi> propoſition.</item>
               <item>Secondly, their reaſons.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition is <hi>revertamur ad Dominum, let us returne to the Lord.</hi> In few words they have ſpoke much.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20533:5"/>
            <p> Their reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Drawne from Gods Juſtice, <hi>Hee hath torne, and he hath ſmitten us,</hi> ideo revertamur, <hi>therefore let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Drawne from Gods mercy, and the profit which ſhall redound to us, <hi>Hee will heale, hee will binde us up:</hi> He is a Chyrurgion that can heale all ſores, a Phyſitian that can cure all diſeaſes, <hi>ideo revertamur, therefore let us returne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Is drawne from Gods power and goodneſſe, he can revive and raiſe us up; though we are now dead in miſery, yet he can revive us; though buryed in the graves of <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> bondage, he can raiſe us up: and this with as much ſpeed as power; after two dayes he will doe it, and if not upon the ſecond, yet hee will bee ſure to doe it upon the third, <hi>&amp; ideo reverta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, come therefore and let us returne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſt of all, here's the happy eſtate we ſhall enjoy after our returne, <hi>We ſhall live in his ſight:</hi> now wee ſuffer a living death in the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> land, where they that hate us are Lords over us, but when once wee returne to the Lord, we ſhall live in his ſight.</p>
            <p>In the propoſition wee have the Perſons, <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah;</hi> their Act, a returne; their Object, to the Lord: Wherein they make:
<list>
                  <item>1. An ingenuous confeſſion of their faults; they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that they had gone aſtray, becauſe they deſire to returne.</item>
                  <item>2. Here's their faith, in that they durſt returne, had they not beleeved in Gods mercy, they would not have come backe to him.</item>
                  <item>3. Their charity, they would not ſteale to him in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20533:6"/>private, nor come alone like <hi>Nicodemus</hi> by night, but all joyne together in the bands of love, with a <hi>venite, Come, let us.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. Heer's their humility, in that they confeſſe, to the glory of Gods juſtice, with <hi>Daniel, tibi Domine juſtitia, nobis confuſio facierum, to thee, O God, belongs juſtice, but to us ſmiting and tearing, as at this day.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. Heer's their hope, in Gods power and goodnes, that as he can, ſo he will revive, he will raiſe them up.</item>
                  <item>6. Heer's their patience, that they would tarry the Lords leiſure, not only to the ſecond, but till the third day; <hi>and bleſſed are all they that wait,</hi> Iſaiah 30.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Laſt of all, which is the Crowne of all, <hi>they ſhould live in his ſight,</hi> which was, They ſhould leade the life of Grace here, and that ſhould conduct them to the life of Glory hereafter.</p>
            <p>And theſe parts are <hi>diſtillatio favi,</hi> the voluntary droppings of this Honey-combe; which I intend to ſpeake of with much plaineneſſe, the ſadneſſe of this time, and ſubject, will admit no deſcant; ſicke men muſt ſigh and groane out their words, the whole may ſing and be witty. I begin with the perſons, <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> and their ingenuous confeſſion, That they had gone aſtray, inferr'd out of their <hi>venite &amp; rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamur,</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Come and let us returne.</head>
               <p>THis life is a journey to another, to a better life, 'tis mans way upon earth, ſo ſaid <hi>David,</hi> I am going the way of all the earth, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 2.2. and no long way neither, 'tis but a ſhort walke betwixt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20533:6"/>Cradle and a Grave: But as in a Labyrinth, ſo here, many turnings there are, many aberrations, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Scripture cryes, <hi>cavete,</hi> take heede, for ſtraite is the gate, and narrow is the path which leades to life, and therefore the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> ch. 30.21. tells us of a voyce behinde us, that cryes, <hi>O all ye that paſſe on, turne neither to your right hand nor your left: this is the way walke in it:</hi> The Church is your way, the Prieſt your guide, follow them, and you ſhall finde reſt to your ſoules.</p>
               <p>But alas we are men, &amp; while we cary about us theſe bodies of clay, we ſhall either fall, as the moſt righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man doth, ſeaven times a day, or elſe forſake the right way, as <hi>Baalam</hi> did, who followed the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of unrighteouſnes, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. in many things we all offend, and who can ſay, that when pleaſure and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit have beckned to him, he has not beene ready to ſay to God, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> did to his Maſter, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 19. <hi>Suffer me I pray thee to goe kiſſe them, and I will follow thee:</hi> this is our miſery.</p>
               <p>O but her's our comfort, the errors in our life are not like thoſe in warre, for which all repentance comes too late, no, being out of the way we may get in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; in the valley of <hi>Achor,</hi> there was the doore of hope left open for us, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.15. and we have a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, that tooke compaſſion on them that were out of the way, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.2. who ſent forth his Diſciples to be guides and leaders to all the World; who lift up their voyces like Trumpets, who cry, <hi>heus vos,</hi> O all yee that are out of your way, make haſte backe againe, ye that have turned aſide, returne, this is your way, walke in it.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20533:7"/>
               <p> But what is it that ſo makes us looſe our way? O 'tis ſinne, and therefore it is called <hi>tranſgreſſie</hi> from <hi>greſſus,</hi> our going; and whereas it promiſeth us a nearer way and a fairer, as theeves doe the true men, when they leade them into a wood, yet alas 'tis meere deceit, and therefore called the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13. 'Tis Gull, a tricke which the grand Cheator put upon our Mother in Paradiſe, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed her the neareſt way to Divinity, but ſhee found the cleane contrary, <hi>Serpens ſeduxit,</hi> the Serpent hath deceived me and led me out of the way. In Hebrew the ſame word goes for ſinne and error, becauſe every ſinne is an error, a turning out of the way which God commands us to walke in, <hi>nonne errant omnes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, Proverbs</hi> 14. <hi>Doe not all ſinners erre?</hi> yes they doe: we may ſee it in two places, 2. <hi>King,</hi> 21.9. where wicked <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> who drew <hi>Iſrael</hi> into hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous abominations, is ſaid <hi>to have led them out of the way;</hi> Gods way, and the way of life, into the Divels way, and way of death: <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> led <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of the way: The ſecond is in the 53. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 3. <hi>God loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked downe from heaven upon the children of men, to ſee if any would underſtand and ſeeke after God,</hi> but hee findes, <hi>they are all gone out of the way:</hi> ſome had bought Farmes, and muſt goe ſee them; ſome yoakes of Oxen, and muſt goe prove them, and ſome had marryed wives, and muſt goe bed them; that is, their affections, like <hi>Siſera</hi> were nailed to the earth, and the wayes of God not once thought on: yet let all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wanderers know that truth of <hi>Solomon: There is a way that ſeemes right to a man in his owne eyes, yet the end thereof is death:</hi> And though ſinne may ſet a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20533:7"/>man a chaire, as it did the ſcorner, in the 1. <hi>Pſalme;</hi> or a ſtoole, as it did in the 94. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> yet they muſt quickly be diſeaſed of both, and lye in Hell, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. No Chaire of State, nor Stoole of eaſe there.</p>
               <p>Ther's none of us I am ſure that would endure that man, who in a ſtrange place (in foule weather) ſhould purpoſely ſet us out of our way, eſpecially we being weary, our beaſts tyred; our Inne a great way off, and the night at hand; ſurely if ever we met with that man again, our blood would riſe at him, and we ſhould have ſomewhat to ſay, yet ſinne leades all out of the way, the way to heaven, and who is angry who falls out with that?</p>
               <p>It leads the old man out of his way, who ſhould make haſte home, death being cloſe at his heeles; and it leads the young man out of his way, and betrayes him to theeves which wound his conſcience, and rob him of his innocence; and often time caſts him into a pit, the pit of deſpaire, from whence there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <p>And therefore, ſeeing young and old; ſeeing all of us, like ſheepe, have gone aſtray, and have turned to our owne wayes, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 53.6. let us make haſte backe againe: and ſeeing, with the Prodigall, we have gone into a farre Countrey (every ſinner goes farre from heaven, and the God of it) our mouthes being fill'd with laughter, and our tongves with joy, let us come backe by <hi>Weeping-Croſſe;</hi> and as travellers love good company, we have in my Text all the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, who having, like us, travelled into the wilderneſſe of Sinne, are now making haſte backe againe, their way is our way; their home, our home: let their faith bee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20533:8"/>our faith too; and their voyce our voyce, we ſtirring up one another as they here doe, <hi>venite &amp; reverta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, Come, let us returne.</hi> So much for the perſons and their ingenuous confeſſion: I come to the next thing, the Act, which they reſolve upon, <hi>revertamur,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Let us returne.</head>
               <p>BVt can a man returne when he will? Hath hee power, as to ſinne, ſo to convert himſelfe from it? Are not the hearts of men in the hands of God, who turnes them like the rivers of water? Why then doth not the Lord ſay, <hi>Egoreducam, I will bring them backe,</hi> but ſuffers them to take it out of his hands with a <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, Come, let us returne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere, they are both true; and the ſecond ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes the former; our returne, Gods preventing grace; by which being led, we freely goe, and the Lord brings us backe to him, yet not without our ſelves; that is, God doth ſo reduce man to himſelfe, that we are neither refractory nor idle, but contribute to our owne happineſſe, as <hi>Ionadab</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Rechab</hi> did in the 1. of <hi>King.</hi> 10. when <hi>Iehu</hi> call'd to him, <hi>give me thy hand, aſcend my Chariot;</hi> ſo we muſt obey the ſweet motions of precious Grace, which ſome men reſiſt to their owne damnation.</p>
               <p>Tis true, the Graces of God inſinuate themſelves by ſecret wayes, and the impreſſions of the will are extreamely nice; all that paſt is, is a dreame, and the future a cloud where thunders murmure in the darke: and though the matter be plaine, to wit, <hi>no man comes to Chriſt, except the Father draw him, Ioh.</hi> 6. yet the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20533:8"/>manner how, is moſt hidden and ſecret. God drawes every man, yet not violently by the head and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; but rather by the eares, with ſweet and gracious perſwaſions. <hi>I let them with the cords of love, Hoſ.</hi> 11.4. God led, but they followed; and leads by peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full love, no rough violence: As the Sun, who breaks neither doores nor windowes to enter into houſes, but penetrates mildly with his gentle beames; ſo Grace finds a quiet paſſage into mans ſoule; which like a chaſte love, being fairely woo'd, is moſt willing to be won.</p>
               <p>Indeed, from the beginning it was not ſo; in our creation there was Gods hand, <hi>faciamus hominem, Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>let us make man;</hi> but in our converſion there is (if I may ſo ſay) but <hi>digitus Dei, the finger of God,</hi> no abſolute irreſiſtable power, for then man might be ſaved without himſelfe, and all the rewards of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue would periſh in the world. But redemption was not wrought to make men idle, and therefore the Scripture divides the childe, ſometimes it gives it to Gods grace, ſometimes to man working by grace. <hi>I will draw them, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Chap. 11. <hi>and they ſhall ſeeke me,</hi> in the verſ. before my Text.</p>
               <p>But to leave the diſpute, and come to the practiſe: The Lord at this inſtant, ſpeakes to every one that heares me, <hi>to returne;</hi> and offers grace ſufficient, to all that will goe about it. Will you ſtand ſtill as <hi>Lots</hi> wife did; and thinke to be raviſhed to heaven by ſome fatall decree? fie no: though mans ſoule bee Gods ſpouſe, as 'tis in the 2. <hi>Chap. ver.</hi> 19. <hi>ſponſabo te mihi,</hi> yet he muſt enjoy thy love by willing contract, not by raviſhment.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20533:9"/>
               <p> And therefore laſie Faith adew, let us acquit our ſelves like men, like Chriſtians, and uſe that Grace which is now offered, and which exerciſe will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove; and ſeeing the gracious Lord of heaven and earth, knockes at the doores of our hearts, to come backe, let us anſwere him with <hi>David paratum eſt cor meum Domine, My heart is ready, O God, my heart is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy;</hi> and ſeeing he calls to us by his Prophet, <hi>Iere.</hi> 3.22. <hi>O yee diſobedient children, returne, and I will heale your backſlidings;</hi> let us take up that anſwere which the Prophet made for them, <hi>Behold we come unto thee, for thou art the Lord our God.</hi> Thus much for the Act <hi>revertamur:</hi> I come to the Object, to whom, that is, <hi>ad Dominum: Let us returne</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Lord.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PEccantes recedunt a Deo, affectuum non locorum ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijs,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ierome, Sinners wander from God, by the diſtance of affections, not of place;</hi> they may goe from his mercies, they can never goe from his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the Prodigall childe, from his fathers houſe, went afar off; but as by ſinning, we depart from God; ſo by forſaking it, we come backe againe; neither can our converſion be right, unleſſe it end in him who is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega. If thou wilt returne, O Iſrael (ſaith the Lord) returne to me, Iere</hi> 4.1. ſome did returne, but it was not to the moſt High, in the 7. <hi>chap.</hi> of this Booke. 16. <hi>ver. they returned from one ſinne to another, as dogs to the vomit, or the ſow that was waſhed, to wallow in the mire:</hi> but theſe are the Devils returnes, <hi>a malo ad pejus;</hi> ours muſt be to the Lord: <hi>Turne ye unto him
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20533:9"/>from whom ye have deeply revolted,</hi> Eſay 21. <hi>from whom we have ſtrayed, to him we muſt goe backe: Againſt thee onely have I ſinned,</hi> Pſal. 51. <hi>and therefore to thee onely will I returne,</hi> Eſay 44.</p>
               <p>Well, theſe men did ſo, and to the honour of their faith be it firſt ſpoken, that although they had ſinned againſt heaven, and the Lord of it, and were of ſonnes become rebels, yet they knew, God remained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, and if they would returne, he would be ſtill their father: though they had loſt their way, they had not as yet loſt their faith, they beleeved God would bee gratious, though they had beene ſinners.</p>
               <p>And this ſparke of faith did kindle in them a holy fire of Charity, which is the next thing obſerveable in their friendly compellation, <hi>venite, come let us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though every man had gone after his owne luſts, and ſcattered their wayes to ſtrange gods, <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.13. yet now they will not onely mend one, but one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſuch is their Charity, that they will not ſteale, no not to heaven, but ſtirre up all to go; you heare no laſie Solifidians <hi>creditè,</hi> nor the Centurions <hi>Ite,</hi> goe thou, go he, but the Saints community, <hi>venite, come let us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this was that which proved their faith to bee quick and legitimate: Faith in God, neither ought, nor can bee without charity to our neighbour: Faith is a good huſwife and lives by her worke, ſhe cryes for them as <hi>Rachel</hi> did for iſſue, give me children or I die. <hi>Non quaerit quae ſunt ſuae,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. <hi>Shee ſeekes not her owne;</hi> ſhe was not ſo nobly borne to be her owne center, and Divinity, but like the Sun, to do good to all.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:20533:10"/>
               <p> St. <hi>Iren.</hi> cals it a preſent from heaven, the top and Zenith of all vertues, it is the gate of the Sanctuary, which leades us to the viſion of the Trinity, 'tis the double ſpirit, which <hi>Eliſha</hi> required, wherewith to love God and our neighbour.</p>
               <p>You are not much to afflict your ſelves to become perfect: (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) Love God, and then doe what you will: And if you would know whether your love to God be reall; mark how you love your neighbour; by how much the lines draw nearer to one another, by ſo much the more they approach the Center: by how much the nearer you approach to your neighbour in love, by ſo much the nearer you are to God.</p>
               <p>In the old Law the <hi>Iewes</hi> were commanded to lift an Oxe or an Aſſe out of the Pit, into which they were fallen: <hi>Numquid Deo cura de Bobus? What, hath God care of Oxen?</hi> ſurely he hath more of men, by how much man comes nearer to his Nature, than does the Oxe or the Aſſe: And it was our Saviours charge to St. <hi>Peter Luke</hi> 22. <hi>Thou being converted, ſtrengthen thy brethren:</hi> Peter, <hi>loveſt thou me? then feede my ſheepe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee are members of that one body, whoſe head is Chriſt: and as in the naturall, ſo in this myſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; one member has neede of another member: the head is to inſtruct the hand, and the hand to guard the head; the eye muſt ſee for the foote, elſe they will both fall into the Ditch: And this St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls <hi>the fulfilling of the Law, Rom.</hi> 13.10. For the Law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands no more than to love: <hi>And a more delicate warre</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chryſologus</hi>) <hi>was never heard of, than to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20533:10"/>conquer all by love:</hi> and St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> obſerves, that all the volumes of the Scriptures are to be found in this one word, <hi>Love,</hi> in this all religion hath her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation.</p>
               <p>Surely Charity is a ſacred flame, kindled in our breaſts by the God of Nature; 'tis the ſoule and life of the whole World; it knowes no more how to hide it ſelfe, than fire does in ſtraw; for as fire will bewray it ſelfe by light and heate, ſo will Divine Charity; it gives light by holy examples, and heat by pious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, <hi>teaching and admoniſhing one another,</hi> Col. 3.16.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Donatiſts</hi> would to heaven alone, as wee have ſome, who will allow ſalvation to none, but them of their faction: whereas the bleſſed St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have ventured to be accurſed for the ſalvation of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and theſe good men here judged it, in glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous piety, a piece of repentance, to be repented of, to returne to the Lord alone; fearing (perhaps) GOD would give them that anſwer, which <hi>Ioſeph did the</hi> Patriarchs: <hi>Gen.</hi> 42. <hi>You ſhall not ſee my face, unleſſe you bring your brother with you:</hi> this made them move together like the fingers of one hand, like the eyes of the ſame head; and in love, that might invite the eyes of Angels, locke arme in arme, and as if they had had but one ſoule, to ſay with one voyce, <hi>venite, come let us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Note againe out of their <hi>venite,</hi> what we may think of thoſe, who neither returne to God themſelves, nor ſuffer others, but are as the Authors of their Schiſme, ſo the hinderers of their converſion.</p>
               <p>Truely we may fafely judge, that they are not of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20533:11"/>Chriſts fold who miſ-leade his ſheepe: and it was a ſinne, which made Lucifer the Divel to draw the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels away from God; and they who on earth goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to divide Chriſts ſeamleſſe coat, the Church; ſhew that they are not members of his body.</p>
               <p>Union builds Gods Church, but Schiſme puls it downe: and judge you, whether it be not a greater ſin then Idolatry, when it was puniſhed with a greater vengeance then Idolatry; the greateſt Idolatry of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> was to be puniſhed with the Sword, <hi>Ex.</hi> 32. but to deſtroy Church Rebels, the Lord did a new thing on earth; and made that earth which fed the peacefull, devoure the factious <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who went downe quicke into the grave, and becauſe they were ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to live, the Lord ſcarce permitted them to dye: but gave them that deadly <hi>vae</hi> of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11 7. <hi>Woe to them by whom offences, come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was <hi>Ieroboams</hi> brand ſet upon him by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that he made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſinne, and brought that Schiſme into the Church, which rent 10 Tribes, not onely from the Scepter, but the God of <hi>Iudah:</hi> As for himſelfe, hee lived to ſee his Altars cracke under the horrour of his new religion, and his poſterity were ſo cloſely purſued by the wrath of God, that in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of a ſhort time, there was not a handfull of the duſt of his houſe left alive upon the face of the earth, and the miſerable Tribes whom he ſeduced, were loſt in forraigne captivity, and ſcattered as ſo much duſt before the wind, or as ſo many ſtrawes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a wrought ſea.</p>
               <p>And thus (in <hi>Euſebius</hi>) the famous Schiſmaticke <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatus,</hi> ſwore all his Communicants upon the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20533:11"/>that they ſhould adhere to his Sect, and never more returne to the Orthodox <hi>Cornelius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Church at unity with her children, is the faireſt among women, but when once torne in ſunder, by ſeverall Factions, ſhe prooves like the Levites divided Concubine; the horrour and deteſtation of every eye.</p>
               <p>The ſpeedieſt way to ſet a man at variance with God, is to be at oppoſition with his brother; and what a ſhame is it, that Theeves and Murderers ſhould goe more friendly to hell, than Chriſtians doe to he even.</p>
               <p>O that our Novatian brood, they of the ſeparation, would conſider this, who diſpoſe Heaven to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but them of their brother and ſiſterhood; would they would remember, That heaven was made for more then for themſelves, though they entitle God to a cruell Decree, and paſſe the ſentence of Reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, upon all that are not as mad as themſelves: Yet maugre their malice, all are their brethren that can ſay, <hi>Our Father;</hi> brethren by a threefold tye that is not eaſily broken, by the ſame Father, God; by the ſame mother, the Church; by the ſame Redeemer, Chriſt: And therefore I will beſeech all Chriſtians, in the powerfull words of an Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>by the Name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that they would be perfectly joyned together in the ſame judgement, and the ſame minde, that yee all ſpeake the ſame things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if ye now hope to reeſtabliſh your broken peace with God,<note place="margin">The newes Carryer of <hi>Ipſwich.</hi>
                  </note> you muſt be at unity with his Church; Let the ſeditious man, who ſowed his tares by night, his Pamphlet in your ſtreets, rayle on, till the accuſer of his brethren (the Devill) who ſet him
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20533:12"/>on worke pay him his wages: as for our ſelves, the way to recover our union with God, lies in the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py agreement with one another, when you all ſay with one heart and one voyce, what <hi>Iſrael</hi> here did, <hi>venite &amp; revertamur ad Dominum, come let us, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo I paſſe from the propoſition, with its adjuncts, faith and charity, to the reaſons, whereof the firſt is drawn <hi>A Iuſtitia Dei, from Gods Iuſtice.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For he hath torne, and he hath ſmitten us.</head>
               <p>ANd this may ſeeme a ſtrange reaſon, that a man ſhould returne to him, by whom he is ſore woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and kiſſe that hand, to whoſe ſeverity he owes the loſſe of blood; as if <hi>David</hi> ſhould embrace <hi>Saul</hi> for running at him with a javelin.</p>
               <p>Yet ſuch is the wholeſome power of affliction, that whom faire words could not returne, rough blowes will bring backe againe; and the Prodigall childe did more at the urgence of hunger and could, than at the teares, and oratory of his Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ionah</hi> in faire weather would be running from God, but the tempeſt and the Whale brought him backe againe. Nay, a Dungeon freed <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> from the Pit of Hell; had he not beene chained in <hi>Babilon,</hi> he had gone on in ſinne, till hee had beene bound hand and foote and caſt into utter darkneſſe.</p>
               <p>This people, who in proſperity, (like <hi>Balaam</hi>) rode poaſt to ſinne, yet when Divine vengeance drew up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, as the Angel did upon him, then downe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their faces, and cry, <hi>If it diſpleaſe the Lord, wee will goe backe againe, Numb.</hi> 22. Theſe who before
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20533:12"/>made the holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ceaſe, yet now the rod is upon them, ſue to him without ceaſing, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie that which the Lord ſpake in the verſe before, <hi>in anguſtijs manè requirent me, in their afflictions they will ſeeke me earely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truely in this, men uſe God, as children doe fruite trees, throw ſtickes at them in faire weather, but when once a ſtorme comes, runne under them for ſhelter.</p>
               <p>The Lord could not otherwiſe ſcowre <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but with the file of afflictions; they would not looke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Maker, untill the deſtroyer was come forth; nor turne backe, till judgement trode on their heeles: this indeede prevailed more with them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpeaking a word, than God, and all his Prophets could with their paſſionate Sermons.</p>
               <p>The Almighty threatned them two verſes before this: <hi>I will be a Lyon unto</hi> Ephraim, <hi>and as a yong Lyon to the houſe of</hi> Judah; <hi>I will teare, even I, and none ſhall reſcue them:</hi> yet threatning would doe no good, no newes as yet of their converſion; but when the wrath of God had brought the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> troopes into their land, and they beganne to bathe their ſwords in their bowels, then every man to his knees, <hi>O Iſrael!</hi> venite &amp; revertamur, <hi>come, and let us returne to the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O how powerfull is Juſtice to ſave, when grace comes with it: theſe, who before forgat God and themſelves; yet now in their miſeries remember both: they, who before ſought after pleaſures and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, <hi>yet now when the Lord ſlew them, then they ſought him, Pſal.</hi> 78.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:20533:13"/>
               <p>'Tis true, Reprobates will not owne God in his Judgements, unleſſe extreame; nothing can ſtartle ſome but thunder; yet good natures will repent at the firſt blow, and like gracious children, kneele to the mothers for mercy at one whipping.</p>
               <p>Theſe men could diſcerne the Lord through the thickeſt troopes of the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Armies, and in the middeſt of their ſwords, confeſſe it was his hand, not King <hi>Iareb,</hi> nor <hi>Salmanaſer,</hi> nor chance, but <hi>Dominus rapuit, the Lord hath ſmittenus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus, as in <hi>Sampſons</hi> riddle, <hi>Out of the Eater came forth meate,</hi> when out of this tearing Lyon they could gather the honey of comfort, making Gods wrath an argument of his love, and returne they will, becauſe he hath ſmitten them.</p>
               <p>Now their argument may bee framed thus: 'Tis Gods Nature (ſay they) to puniſh where he affects, and to chaſten every ſonne whom he loves: Now like a juſt father, he hath ſmitten us, but to breake our ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks, not our bones; though he puniſhes our ſinnes, yet he pitties our humanity; like a wiſe Chyrurgion he has torne us, yet not to kill, but cure our feſtered ſores: hee is <hi>ſalus Iſrael,</hi> Jer. 3. <hi>the health of Iſraell;</hi> therefore let us returne.</p>
               <p>And thus, like <hi>Iob,</hi> they acknowledge affliction com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not out of the duſt, nor miſery ſpring out of the earth; and therefore reſolve with that Champion of heaven, Though the Lord teares and ſlaies us, yet will we truſt in him.</p>
               <p>And happy are they who ſo kiſſe the ſonne, when he is firſt angry, and fall upon their knees, before his whole diſpleaſure bee aroſe; a teare may doe that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20533:13"/>with God in time, which afterwards a ſhower of blood cannot.</p>
               <p>But thrice miſerable they, who when they feele the rod, yet will not ſee the hand, but arme themſelves with Paſt-boord againſt the murthering Canon, and begge of the creature helpe againſt the Creator.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Aſa</hi> in his diſeaſe ſought to the Phyſitian, not the Lord: thus <hi>Iobs</hi> Wife in her husbands miſery, when he ſhould have kneel'd to Prayer, fell to cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: Thus wicked <hi>Ahaziah</hi> turn'd from the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to ſeeke helpe from <hi>Baalzebub,</hi> the god of <hi>Eckron;</hi> but all theſe knockt at a wrong doore, and tooke great paines to goe to hell: <hi>Thou turneſt man to deſtruction:</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) Againe thouſai'ſt, <hi>come again ye children of men:</hi> And as <hi>Hannah</hi> ſung, 1 of <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. <hi>It is the Lord that kils and makes alive, that brings downe to the grave, and lifts up againe,</hi> ideo revertamur, cries <hi>Iſrael, therefore let us returne:</hi> and this is the firſt argument: the ſecond is drawne, <hi>A miſericordia dei, from Gods mercy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>He will heale, he will binde us up.</head>
               <p>A Metaphor taken from Phyſitians and Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons: the <hi>Septuagint</hi> turnes it, <hi>alligabit ſicut faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cijs, he will binde us up as with ſwathes,</hi> as Chyrurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doe ſores till they are whole: St. <hi>Ierome</hi> uſes the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>linteola,</hi> Linnen ragges put by a Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon into wounds, to eate out the corrupt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>Indeed in Iſraels recovery the Lord uſed much Art, and played the skilfull Chyrurgeon: firſt he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20533:14"/>applyed ſharpe corroſives to eate out the feſtered corruption; judgement to eate out ſinne; then he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled their broken ſpirits with his mercy, and ſwathed them with a gratious pardon: ſo <hi>David: Hee forgives thy ſinnes and heales althy infirmities, Pſal.</hi> 103.</p>
               <p>Their diſeaſe would admit no Phyſitian but God, to him alone belong the iſſues of life and death: the balmes of <hi>Gilead</hi> were antidotes too weake; for the oyle of the Scorpion muſt heale his owne ſtinge, and the ſight of the Brazen Serpent expell the poyſon of the fiery Serpent.</p>
               <p>In the chapter before, ver. 13. <hi>When</hi> Ephraim <hi>ſaw his ſickneſſe, and</hi> Iudah <hi>his wound, then went</hi> Ephraim <hi>to the</hi> Aſſyrian, <hi>and ſent to King</hi> Iareb <hi>for helpe, yet could he not heale, nor cure you of your wound.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No ſaid <hi>Ier.</hi> 3. <hi>in vaine is ſalvation hoped for from the Hils and mountaines (the Kings and great men of the earth.) God is the health of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. ſo that now they conclude with <hi>Solomon, Proverbs</hi> 21. <hi>There is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prudence, nor councell, nor wiſedome againſt the Lord:</hi> What is the Phyſitian over his patient without God? but a buſie Ant, ſtriving to put life into a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. There is no flying from him, but to him; from the hand of his juſtice, to the armes of his mercy, and looke how much the arme in length exceedes the hand; by ſo much his mercy, to the penitent, is exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded beyond his juſtice.</p>
               <p>O! this is a ſafer Sanctuary, than was <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Temple: his favour is a ſtronger protection, than ever were the hornes of the Altar, and therefore the Prophet calls them, <hi>the ſure mercies of David:</hi> mens mercies are ſometimes cruell, alwaies deceitful;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20533:14"/>but Gods are ſure mercies, ſuch as never failed any ſoule that truſted in him.</p>
               <p>And though the ſame Phyſicke which helpes an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, will not cure a Fever, yet the ſame mercy which helpes the ſoule of one ſinne, can cure it of all: <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to me,</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>and I will heale all thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions,</hi> Jer. 3.22.</p>
               <p>And therefore out of this booke, let me take up one peeble, to throw againſt the brow of the Gyant <hi>Deſpaire:</hi> though the Lord, like an inraged Lyon, does ſmite, and teare us with his judgements, yet wee here learne, if we will returne, he wil heale us, hee will binde us up, and why will he? O, becauſe with him there are multitude of mercies, with him there is plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous redemption; and with this hope, Iſrael in captivity, did now even guild their chaines.</p>
               <p>It was propheſied in the fourth of <hi>Malach. ver.</hi> the ſecond: <hi>Vnto them that feare my name ſhall he come, with healing upon his wings:</hi> Who is <hi>(Hee)</hi> that ſhall come? O 'tis <hi>Meſsiah</hi> the Saviour of the World, hee ſhall come with wings, to ſhew his ſpeede, that he will even flye to be mercifull.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he ſhall come with infinite vertue, and unſpeakable comfort, hee ſhall come with healing upon his Wings; and therefore never feare your <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabit,</hi> but God will heale, and bind you up; and this is the ſecond argument: The third is drawne, <hi>A poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, &amp; bonitate Dei, from Gods power and goodneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:20533:15"/>
               <head>After two dayes hee will revive us, the third day hee will raiſe us up.</head>
               <p>AMong many opinions, of theſe dayes, I will name but one, and that is of them, who by two dayes, underſtand a ſhort time, by the third, a long time, and both of them uncertaine, whoſe accompliſhment they might not know, but ought to expect, <hi>and bleſſed is he that waites,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Prophet, Dan.</hi> 12. but curſed is he that ſaies with the King of <hi>Iſrael, Why ſhould I waite upon the Lord any longer,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 6.33. Now if two dayes bee taken for a ſhort time, then the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment runs thus:</p>
               <p>The time wherein we are to be afflicted, is no long time, therefore never deſpaire, 'tis but two dayes, no more, and therefore (O yee ſeede of <hi>Abraham</hi>) beare your Croſſe with patient ſpirits, your afflictions are not everlaſting afflictions, <hi>though heavineſſe may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for a night, yet joy will come in the morning,</hi> and if not the firſt, yet ſure enough upon the ſecond, <hi>Poſt biduum, after two dayes he will revive us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if the third day bee taken for along time, then thus: The Lord can raiſe a carkaſſe, as well after three dayes, when it beginnes to ſmell and putrifie, as the firſt day and houre it dyed. <hi>Eliſhas</hi> Coffin raiſed a man that had beene many yeares dead, as eaſily as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> did the childe that had been ſo but a few houres. Now if Prophets could doe thus, ſurely the God of thoſe Prophets could doe much more; and therefore, although three daies (that is along time) we have laine in the grave of our captivity, yet the Lord can raiſe us up.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:20533:15"/>
               <p> Some have undertaken to ſhew theſe three dayes in the Chapter before my Text, at whoſe, 14. ver. the Lord ſaid, <hi>He would be a Lyon to</hi> Ephraim, <hi>and</hi> Iudah, and would teare them as a Lyon doth his prey, and ſell them for nothing to the Kings of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon:</hi> and this may be the firſt day, <hi>Dies Crucis, &amp; Mortis,</hi> The day of their death.</p>
               <p>Secondly, at the 15. ver. <hi>I will goe ſaith the Lord to mine owne place,</hi> I will waſh mine hands of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as a people that are dead, and buried; they ſhall lie in deſperate captivity without Prince, Prieſt, <hi>Ephod,</hi> and <hi>Teraphin,</hi> and this is the ſecond day, <hi>Dies ſepulturae,</hi> The day of their buriall.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the Lord ſayes in that ſame ver. he would not forſake them for ever, <hi>Donec, Vntill they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged their faults, and ſought him,</hi> no longer: ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that after thoſe dayes, of death, and buriall, hee would returne, and put new life into his people; which is to be underſtood, not carnally, but ſpiritually; and reſpects not onely their deliverance out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> but their freedome from the ſlavery of ſinne, and hell, to be accompliſhed ere long by <hi>Emmanuel,</hi> the Savior of the world. Now, out of their <hi>Vivificabit</hi> we may learne, that mans beſt life comes from Gods grace: unleſſe he revive us with his Spirit, wee are dead in ſinne, like the Widow in pleaſure: 1 Tim. 5. <hi>She was dead, though alive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, theſe men buried in miſeries; cry, <hi>Vive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, We ſhall live;</hi> to teach, that life is to be hoped for in the jawes of death; and though the Grave gapes never ſo wide, yet it cannot devoure the Article of our Reſurrection. <hi>Wherefore my ſpirit and fleſh ſhall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20533:16"/>reſt in hope; for though after my skin, wormes deſtroy this body, yet with theſe eyes I ſhall ſee God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, here are Gods children in the darke night of Captivity, raiſing arguments of comfort, to helpe one another; teaching that man ſhould never deſpaire of Gods goodneſſe, or his owne Salvation, but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in hope, though againſt hope: He that is good to himſelfe, neede not feare that God will be ill to him.</p>
               <p>Would time permit, I might ſhew you how this Text was verified upon <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and how upon each Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; how <hi>Chriſt</hi> had theſe three dayes of <hi>Death, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall,</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> upon whom God did let fly, like an enraged Lyon, did teare, and ſmite him in the day of his fierce wrath; and how each Chriſtian muſt drinke after him in this bitter cup, and in this life paſſe through the <hi>Iewes</hi> purgatory.</p>
               <p>But I haſten to the period of all, which like <hi>Iobs</hi> latter end, is better than his beginning, which ſtands like a beloved harbour beyond a churliſh ſea; which looks like a cleare Heaven after a battaile of clouds, and thunder; 'tis <hi>Viſio Dei</hi> after all theſe tearings, and ſmitings, deaths, and burials, <hi>Vivemus coram eo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>We ſhall live in his ſight.</head>
               <p>ANd this is no meane happineſſe, to live in Gods ſight; in the laſt Chapter, <hi>the Lord turned his backe upon them,</hi> and did what he threatned, <hi>Ier</hi> 7.15. <hi>I will caſt you out of my ſight:</hi> And this <hi>Cain</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to be no light puniſhment, but one greater than he could beare. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Behold, thou haſt dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20533:16"/>mee out this day from the face of the earth, and from thy face ſhall I bee bid; and it ſhall come to paſſe, that every one that findes mee, ſhall ſlay mee.</hi> Some affirme, that whereſoever <hi>Caine</hi> ſet his foote, the earth trembled: and <hi>Procopius</hi> adds a tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that hee perpetually ſaw certaine Spectres with ſwords of fire, which brought horrible af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frightments upon him; the truth whereof I know not.</p>
               <p>Yet this I am ſure of, no ſword could be more fiery than that of his conſcience, which every moment, with hidden launches, did open his breaſt and made him thinke every creature he met, ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him a murder.</p>
               <p>And ſuch is the eſtate of every one whom God turnes his backe upon; but now, it was <hi>Iſraels</hi> comfort, that the Lords face was turned to them; his favour, and protection; and though hitherto they had been caſt out of both, yet now they ſhould live in his ſight.</p>
               <p>In a word, the life which the Prophet here meanes was primarily, a temporall life, ſeconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, an eternall life; abſolutely the life of Grace, by conſequence, that of Glory: So the <hi>Chaldee para.</hi> renders my Text, <hi>vita donabit nos in diebus conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis qui venturi ſunt, in die reſurrectionis mortuoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuſcitabit nos, &amp; vivemus coram eo.</hi> That is, <hi>wee ſhall leade a happy life here, and a glorified life hereafter:</hi> theſe two following one another, like the twinnes out of <hi>Rebecca's</hi> wombe; the later laying hold upon the former, and more then theſe two, no covetous Jew could deſire.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:20533:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> I cannot ſtay to ſhew you how this Propheſie was verified upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> &amp; <hi>Iudah;</hi> whom the Lord, after ſeventy yeares captivity, raiſed from the graves of <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> bondage, and brought them back to that <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which they beheld with as many tears of joy, as they remembred with ſorrow, <hi>when they ſate down by the Waters of Babylon;</hi> where again they lived in Gods ſight, until new ſinnes provoked a more conſuming wrath, and the <hi>Romans,</hi> for cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying theire innocent <hi>Meſsiah,</hi> made the Jewes blood as cheape as their mothers teares.</p>
               <p>The few ſands which are yet behinde, ſhall run forth in a ſhort review of my Text, by way of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication; and ſo Ile commend you to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Come let us returne to the Lord &amp;c.</head>
               <p>HAd <hi>Hoſea</hi> uttered his Propheſie the laſt yeare, it would have beene hard to ſay, whether hee meant <hi>Iſrael</hi> or <hi>England:</hi> the Sceanes are the ſame, onely the Actors differ; both of us have beheld a Tragedy commenced in our owne blood: <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> bore the firſt part, <hi>London</hi> the ſecond. <hi>Lord how are we ſpoyled?</hi> ſaid the Prophet of them; and may not I ſay ſo of this place? A City undone, and no man the richer: Above 1200 ſlaine, and no ſword ſeen; <hi>Lord how are we ſpoyled? How is Ieruſalem become a deſolate widow?</hi> It was the Lamentation of <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> and may it not be revived upon <hi>London?</hi> how was ſhe forſaken, not onely of her children, but of her God, and many moneths ſate, like <hi>Rachel, wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for her children and would not be comforted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:20533:17"/>
               <p> Your doores which were uſed to be opened to your friends, were ſhut up by diſeaſe; and the very caſements whereat you tooke the breath of life, did let in death: ſo that wee may cry with <hi>Iſrael, The Lord hath torne, and the Lord hath ſmitten us,</hi> and as the Magicians ſaid of the lice of <hi>Egypt, Exod.</hi> 8.16. They were <hi>digitus Dei, the finger of God;</hi> Wee may of our Viſitation, 'twas <hi>manus Dei, the hand of God;</hi> and therefore we call it <hi>plaga, a ſtroake,</hi> a blow from heaven.</p>
               <p>Yet ſee the goodneſſe of the moſt high; no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner had we, by the appoyntment of our moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraigne, run to the ſecond of <hi>Ioel,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed a Faſt; called a ſolemne aſſembly, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Iſrael, venite &amp; revertamur, O come, let us returne unto the Lord.</hi> But that power, who repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of making us, did alſo repent of deſtroying us; and ſaid, <hi>My Spirit ſhall not alwaies contend with man, leaſt the ſoules which I have made, ſhould faile before me. Iſai.</hi> 57.</p>
               <p>And as <hi>Ieremiah</hi> cryed, <hi>God is the health of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. ſo may I, God is become the health of <hi>London:</hi> it was not the Froſt, nor the Snow, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of natures colds, throwne downe from thoſe moving ſhops of Meteors, but <hi>Dominus ſanauit, the Lord hath healed, the Lord hath bound us up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now let me direct my ſpeech to you, right Honourable, and the inhabitants of this City, and ſay in the words of the Saviour of the World; <hi>Art thou made whole? ſinne no more, leaſt a worſe thing happen to thee:</hi> though yee have eſcaped the laſt yeares contagion; yet there is a <hi>Tophet</hi> in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20533:18"/>
                  <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> where plagues are eternall.</p>
               <p>And therefore let every man beginne a reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at home, &amp; as thoſe cryed out, much more will I, <hi>every man to his tents, O</hi> Iſrael; <hi>to his conſcience, O</hi> London. <hi>Now looke to thine owne houſe David.</hi> I make no queſtion, but much coſt and labour has beene beſtowed in ayring and cleanſing your hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; but it is to no purpoſe, unleſſe you ſweepe out ſinne, which <hi>Solomon</hi> calls, <hi>the plague of the heart,</hi> turne that out of your ſhops and conſciences, it will prove a better antidote, than all the Pitch, Rue, and Franckincenſe in the World.</p>
               <p>Infect the aire no more with your oathes and courteous equivocations; make not your ſelves worſe in belying your wares, that they are better: the moſt winning eloquence a tradeſ-man can ſpeake, is truth, and the beſt way to thrive apace, is to pray.</p>
               <p>Look not upon the next life, as <hi>Mathematitions</hi> do at heaven, through a cranney, or hole, out of a darke Chamber, which renders it poore and ſmall; not venture your hopes of heaven, like <hi>Cain,</hi> to build upon earth.</p>
               <p>Raiſe not the walls of your houſes with the ruine of Gods houſe, or your neighbours; nor pay your Lecturers with your Parſons tithes: let not the wrack't out blood of the Tenant cry againſt you, nor your workmens wages be kept backe.</p>
               <p>Uſe not falſe lights, and a deceitfull ballance, wherein your ſoules are put and found too light. And beleeve me, before it is too late, <hi>Godlineſſe is great gaine,</hi> and there's no ſuch policy in this
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20533:18"/>World, as to bee an honeſt man.</p>
               <p>And you my Lord, and your brethren, to whom the government of this City is committed, I know, you have taken all the courſes, that wiſedome can thinke of, to ſtay the infection, when there is but one way to doe it, that is, to make your Citizens good: but you will ſay, 'tis God that muſt doe this, you cannot; tis true, your part is only to ſhew them the way by a good example: and ſeeing your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is the firſt wheele, whereunto all others are faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; it is neceſſary that you give a good motion; for it is held by ſome Aſtronomers, that when the Sunne ſtood ſtill in the time of <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> the Moone and Starres kept the like pauſe.</p>
               <p>Now, if you that are Governours, would have the <hi>Plague</hi> a ſtranger in the City, then ſee that in your Courts of Iudicature, <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> kiſſe each other: <hi>Let juſtice runne downe like water, and righteouſneſſe as the river, Amos</hi> 5.24. It will clenſe the City better, then all your Conduits let looſe upon Sundayes.</p>
               <p>Suffer not the wicked Advocate, who plowes lies, and exchanges God for a bribe, to put Trueth upon the Rack, and ſtretch a Clients cauſe with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes, as the Shoomaker doth Leather with his teeth: theſe men are our Plagues in the times of health, and it put Gods mercy to a ſtand, when in <hi>Ieruſalem there was not found a man that executed juſtice,</hi> Iet. 5. <hi>How ſhall I pardon thee for this?</hi> (ſaith the Lord, <hi>ver.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>But God hath ſet you on high to no other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, then to puniſh vice beneath you; and if you
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20533:19"/>ſuffer that to riſe, it will trample you under foote; and therefore, continue my Lord, like a good <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> to ſtand in the gap; pleade before God the cauſe of his people with your prayers; and before his people, the cauſe of God with your ſword.</p>
               <p>And let me beſeech all that heare me, that they would leave no ſparkes of ſinne raked up in their conſciences, leaſt the fire of Gods wrath breakes out againe more furiouſly the next ſpring.</p>
               <p>Verifie the firſt part of my Text, <hi>Returne to the Lord with all your hearts, with all your ſoules;</hi> and he will verifie the ſecond, <hi>ſanabit, hee will heale, hee will binde us up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though for two dayes, you, and your ſhops, and your tradings have laine dead, yet there's a third day, <hi>wherein God will raiſe you up, and make you live in his ſight,</hi> where Divine protection ſhall watch over you here, and keepe all Plagues from your bodies, as the Nurſe does flyes from the face of her ſleeping childe, till you enter into the other viſion of God, the ſight of Glory; where our miſeries can have no beginning, nor our felicity any ending; where youth ſhall not waxe old, nor health impaire, but theſe bodies, which are now the ſhops of all diſeaſes, ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as impaſſible as Angels, as ſubtile as rayes of light, as radiant as the Sunne, and as ſwift as the wings of thunder, and we ſhall lead no other life than that of God; of the knowledge of God, of the love of God; and that as long as God ſhall be God: and therefore, <hi>venite &amp; revertamur ad Dominum.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:20533:19"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Come, and let us returne to the Lord, for hee hath torne, and hee will heale us, hee hath broken, and hee will binde us up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>After two dayes hee will revive us, the third day hee will raiſe us up, and we ſhall live in his ſight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which God of his mercy grant, &amp;c.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
